Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
- Other Monographs
  - Andrews, Charles McLean, ed. Narratives of the Insurrections, 1675-1690. Original Narratives of Early American History. 1915., 84; 414 pp.; facsim.
    1) T. M. [Thomas Mathew], "The Beginning, Progress and Conclusion of Bacons Rebellion in Virginia in the Years 1675 and 1676," 1705, Library of Congress. Mathew, a merchant-planter in Northumberland County, represented Stafford County in the 1676 session of the House of Burgesses and was an eyewitness to many events he described. His narrative has been printed in several sources (see Andrews, p. 14). 2) ["The History of Bacon's and Ingram's Rebellion," 1676], Virginia Historical Society. The unknown author evidently was a Virginian who was familiar with the course of the rebellion and obtained some of his evidence as an eyewitness. Some leaves of the document are missing from the beginning and the end. Two versions have been printed in Massachusetts Historical Society publications (see Andrews, pp. 45-46).
    3) "A True Narrative of the Rise, Progresse, and Cessation of the Late Rebellion in Virginia, Most Humbly and Impartially Reported by His Majestyes Commissioners Appointed to Enquire into the Affaires of the Said Colony," 1677, two copies: Public Record Office (C.O. 5/1371) and Pepysian Library, Magdalene College, Cambridge. The report was signed by commissioners John Berry and Francis Moryson. The volumes in which the copies are to be found at the PRO and at Cambridge also contain copies of many letters and papers written or received by the commissioners.Reprint: Bowie, Md., Heritage Books, 1992.
  - Andrews, Matthew Page. The Soul of a Nation: The Founding of Virginia and the Projection of New England. 1943., 85; Xiii, 378 pp.; illus.
    Includes bibliographical references, and an index.
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities. Being the Year Book of the Association...including the Association Years 1951 through 1959. 1959., 86; 126 pp.; illus. (part col.)
  - ---. Jamestown, the Cradle of the United States of America. 1901., 87; 15 pp.
  - ---, Jamestown Committee. Reports of the Excavations Made at the Church at Jamestown. 1902., 88; 11 pp.
  - Axtell, James. The Rise and Fall of the Powhatan Empire: Indians in Seventeenth-Century Virginia. The Foundations of America [series]. 1995., 89; 42 pp.; illus., maps, portraits.
    Tells the story of the English settlement of Virginia from the perspective of both the colonists and the Indians. Powhatan is seen as a strong leader who used the English presence to enhance his own position among his people. John Smith was the clever commander who saved Jamestown from starvation and kept peace with the Indians. Pocahontas was a link between the two culturesBibliography: 41-42.
  - Bailey, Francie. Jamestown to Yorktown., 90; [32] pp.; illus.
  - Baldwin-Lima-Hamilton Corporation, and Standard Steel Works. Exhibit by the Baldwin Locomotive Works and the Standard Steel Works, Philadelphia, Pa., U.S.A.: Jamestown Ter-centennial Exposition, Norfolk, Va. 1907., 91; 34 pp.; illus.
  - Banvard, Joseph. Romance of American History, as Illustrated in the Early Events Connected with the French Settlement at Fort Carolina, the Spanish Colony at St. Augustine, and the English Plantation at Jamestown., 92; 306 pp.; front., illus.
    Banvard's National Series of American Histories, [vol. 3].
  - ---. Southern Explorers and Colonists, as Illustrated in the Early Events Connected with the French Settlement at Fort Carolina, the Spanish Colony at St. Augustine, and the English Plantation at Jamestown. Pioneers of the New World, [vol. 2]. 1875., 93; 306 pp.; front., illus.
  - Barbour, Philip L., ed. The Jamestown Voyages under the First Charter, 1606-1609: Documents Relating to the Foundation of Jamestown and the History of the Jamestown Colony up to the Departure of Captain John Smith, Last President of the Council in Virginia under the First Charter, Early in October 1609. 1969., 94; 2 vols.; plates, illus., maps.
    Bibliography: 483-93
    Reprint: Nendeln, Liechtenstein, Kraus Reprint, 1976. 2 vols. in 1 (xviii, 524 pp.) Includes indexes.
  - ---. Pocahontas and Her World: A Chronicle of America's First Settlement in Which Is Related the Story of the Indians and the Englishmen, Particularly Captain John Smith, Captain Samuel Argall, and Master John Rolfe. 1970., 95; Xx, 30 pp.; illus., maps, portraits.
    Bibliography: [283]-299.
  - ---. The Three Worlds of Captain John Smith. 1964., 96; Xix, 553 pp.; illus., tables, maps, portraits.
    A sympathetic biography which finds Smith to have been basically honest in his writings, though prone to exaggeration, in keeping with the inflated and exuberant style of his timesBibliography: 493-527. Includes index.
  - Bastow, Thelma Wilkerson de Shields. What Happened to the Rappahannocks?: The Story of This Once Mighty Tribe of the Great Nation of Powhatan from the Time of the Coming of Those First Englishmen to Jamestown until the Present. 1975., 97; 108 pp.; illus., maps.
  - Bell, Edith (Rathbun), and William Lightfoot Heartwell. Brunswick Story: A History of Brunswick County., 98; 76 pp.; illus., portraits, map.
    Written at the request of the Board of Supervisors, Brunswick County, Virginia, in observance of the 350th anniversary of the settlement of Jamestown Bibliography: 75-76.
  - Beverley, Robert. The History and Present State of Virginia, in Four Parts, by a Native and Inhabitant of the Place., 99; 104, 40, 64, 83, 16 pp.; front., plates, tables.
    The first history of the colony by a native Virginian. The four sections deal with the first settlement of Virginia, natural resources and commerce, the Indians, and the present state of the colony. Louis B. Wright, in his introduction to a 1947 reprint (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press), describes Beverley's account of the early period as sketchy and inaccurate and the weakest portion of the work. His treatment of the Indians, however, is sympathetic and realistic. In a revised edition published in 1722, Beverley softened his comments on personalities and made an effort to restrain his satirical tone.
  - Billings, Warren M. Jamestown and the Founding of the Nation. [1991]., 100; 144 pp.; illus.
    Bibliographical references: 133-43.
  - ---, ed. The Old Dominion in the Seventeenth Century: A Documentary History of Virginia, 1606-1689. Documentary Problems in Early American History [series]. 1975., 101; Xxiv, 324 pp.; illus., maps.
    A collection of primary sources, many not previously printed, intended "to introduce students to some of the raw materials basic to an understanding of both seventeenth-century Virginia and the problem of creating a society in a new world." There is no index to help identify specific references to Jamestown, but Jamestown was at the center of public life in the colony throughout the centuryChapter headings include The Beginnings, The Evolution of Self-government, The Structure of Society, Bound Labor, Tobacco and Trade, Indians and Whites, Upheaval and Rebellion, and Life in Seventeenth-Century Virginia.
  - Billings, Warren M., John E. Selby, and Thad W. Tate. Colonial Virginia: A History. A History of the American Colonies [series]. 1986., 102; Xvii, 420 pp.; illus.
    Bibliography: 375-400. Includes index.
  - Blanton, Wyndham B. Medicine in Virginia in the Seventeenth Century. 1930., 103; Xvii, 337 pp.; illus.
    Bibliography: 298-305Blanton also wrote Medicine in Virginia in the Eighteenth Century (1931) and Medicine in Virginia in the Nineteenth Century (1933).
  - Bolitho, Hector. The Glasshouse, Jamestown, Virginia. 1957., 104; 31 pp.; illus.
    Includes bibliographical references.
  - Bragdon, Kathleen, Cary Carson, Edward Chappell, and Willie Graham. Report on Jamestown Architectural Survey. Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Library Research Reports, no. 336. 1992., 105; 41 leaves; illus.
    Final drawings and structure reports on twenty-five major buildings or complexes of buildings excavated at Jamestown between 1935 and 1956, as requested in National Park Service purchase orders 76359 and 76360.
  - Breen, T. H., ed. Shaping Southern Society: The Colonial Experience. 1976., 106; Viii, 265 pp.
    Contents include "The Labor Problems at Jamestown, 1607-18," by E. S. Morgan; "The Image of the Indian in the Southern Colonial Mind," by G. B. Nash; "A Changing Labor Force and Race Relations in Virginia, 1660-1710," by T. H. Breen; and "Politics and Social Structure in Virginia," by B. Bailyn.
  - Bridenbaugh, Carl. Jamestown, 1544-1699. 1980., 107; Xiv, 199 pp.; illus.
  - Brock, R. A. (Robert Alonzo), and Virgil A. Lewis. Virginia and Virginians: Eminent Virginians; Executives of the Colony of Virginia from Sir Thomas Smyth to Lord Dunmore; Executives of the State of Virginia from Patrick Henry to Fitzhugh Lee; Sketches of Gens. Ambrose Powell Hill, Robert E. Lee, Thos. Jonathan Jackson, Commodore Maury; History of Virginia from Settlement of Jamestown to Close of the Civil War. 1888., 108; 2 vols.; illus.
    The History of Virginia from Settlement of Jamestown to Close of the Civil War was written by Prof. Virgil A. Lewis, revised by Dr. R. A. BrockReprint: Spartanburg, S.C., Reprint Co., 1973.
  - Brooklyn Day at the Jamestown Exposition: Souvenir of a Pilgrimage to the Jamestown Exposition and to Some of the Battlefields of the South, Made during the Week of October 12 to 20, 1907, by a Party of Ladies and Gentlemen from the Borough of Brooklyn. 1908., 109; 47 pp.; illus.
  - Brown, Alexander. English Politics in Early Virginia History. Boston and New York: Houghton, Mifflin and Co. 1901., 110; Vi, 277 pp.
    Attempts to show that a "historic wrong was done our patriotic founders by James I, his commissioned officials, and licensed historians--both in the evidences of the Court party preserved by the crown and in the histories licensed under the crown." John Smith is presented as one of the crown's licensed historians, who distorted the true intent of the Patriot party to plant a popular form of government in the New World.
  - ---. The First Republic in America: An Account of the Origin of This Nation, Written from the Records Then (1624) Concealed by the Council, Rather Than from the Histories Then Licensed by the Crown. Boston and New York: Houghton, Mifflin and Co. 1898., 111; Xxiv, 688 pp.; front.
    A history of Virginia and the Virginia Company of LondonReprint: New York, Russell & Russell, 1969.
  - ---, ed. The Genesis of the United States. Boston: Houghton, Mifflin and Company 1890., 112; 2 vols.; portraits, maps, plans.
    A Narrative of the Movement in England, 1605-1616, which Resulted in the Plantation of North America by Englishmen, Disclosing the Contest between England and Spain for the Possession of the Soil Now Occupied by the United States of America; Set Forth through a Series of Historical Manuscripts Now First Printed Together with a Reissue of Rare Contemporaneous Tracts, Accompanied by Bibliographical Memoranda, Notes, and Brief Biographies [Title page]Includes index.
  - Brown, Stuart E., and Lorraine F. Myers. Pocahontas' Descendants: A Revision, Enlargement, and Extension of the List as Set Out by Wyndham Robertson in His Book Pocahontas and Her Descendants (1887). 3d ed. Baltimore: Genealogical Publishing Co. 1997., 113; Vii, 189 pp.; illus.
    A tentative list of the descendants of Pocahontas, a list set forth in a combined volume (printed in 1994 and reissued in 1997) which includes reprints of the three books Pocahontas' Descendants (ENTRY 360), Corrections and Additions to Pocahontas' Descendants (1992), and Second Corrections and Additions to Pocahontas' Descendants (1994). [Introduction]Includes index.
  - Bruce, Philip Alexander. Economic History of Virginia in the Seventeenth Century: An Inquiry into the Material Condition of the People, Based upon Original and Contemporaneous Records. 1896., 114; 2 vols.
    New York: Macmillan & Co.,
  - ---. Institutional History of Virginia in the Seventeenth Century: An Inquiry into the Religious, Moral, Educational, Legal, Military, and Political Condition of the People, Based on Original and Contemporaneous Records. 1910., 115; 2 vols.
    New York:
  - ---. Social Life of Virginia in the Seventeenth Century: An Inquiry into the Origin of the Higher Planting Class, Together with an Account of the Habits, Customs, and Diversions of the People. Richmond: Printed for the author by Whittet & Shepperson 1907, 116; 268 pp.
    Bibliography: 11-13.
  - Bruno, Michael H., and Cheryl J. Cease. The Insiders' Guide to Williamsburg, Jamestown-Yorktown. 7th ed. Manteo, N.C.: Insider Guides 1996., 117; X, 411 pp.; illus., maps.
    Includes indexes1st ed. (1984) and 2nd ed. (1987) by Donna Quaresima and Susan Bruno (Manteo, N.C.: Storie/McOwen Publishers); 5th ed. (1993) by Michael H. Bruno and Annette McPeters (Richmond: Richmond Times-Dispatch).
  - Brunswick County (Va.) Board of Supervisors. Brunswick County, Virginia, Information for the Homeseeker and Investor. Richmond: Williams Printing Co. 1907., 118; 48 pp.; illus.
    Prepared under the supervision of I. E. Spatig, as authorized by the Board of Supervisors of Brunswick County, July 23, 1906. Compiled by Marvin Smithey On cover: Jamestown Exposition, 1607-1907.
  - Bryan, Isobel Lamont Stewart. To the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities: An Appeal for Funds and New Members in Preparation for the Tri-centennial of the Founding of the Colony at Jamestown. 1905., 119; [22] leaves.
  - Brydon, George MacLaren. Religious Life of Virginia in the Seventeenth Century: The Faith of Our Fathers. Jamestown 350th Anniversary Historical Booklets, no. 10. Williamsburg: Virginia 350th Anniversary Celebration Corp., 51 pp.; illus. 1957., 120
    Bibliography: 46
  - ---. Virginia's Mother Church and the Political Conditions under Which It Grew: An Interpretation of the Records of the Colony of Virginia and of the Anglican Church of That Colony, 1607-1727. Richmond: Virginia Historical Society, 1947., 121
    Xxii, 571 ppIncludes bibliographical references, and an index.
  - Bullard, Julia Wyatt. Jamestown Tributes and Toasts. Lynchburg, Va.: J. P. Bell Co. 1907., 122; 196 pp.; front., illus., portraits.
    Illustrated by Bessie Thorpe Lyle.
  - Burgess, Mary Abigail Smith. Richmond Guide Book: Sketches and Views of Richmond, Virginia, Supplemented by Sketches of Williamsburg, Jamestown, Yorktown; Description and Map, Historic Battlefields. 1909., 123; 87 pp.; illus., folded map.
    Revised and largely rewritten from the author's Sketches and Views, Points of Interest, Richmond, Virginia, 1903 and 1907. Published in 1912 and 1913 as Official Richmond Guide Book.
  - Burk, John Daly. History of Virginia from Its First Settlement to the Present Day. 1804-16., 124
    4 vols.
  - Burke, Edmund, and William Burke. An Account of the European Settlements in America. 1757., 125; 2 vols.; maps.
    In six parts. I. A short history of the discovery of that part of the world. II. The manners and customs of the original inhabitants. III. Of the Spanish settlements. IV. Of the Portuguese. V. Of the French, Dutch, and Danish. VI. Of the English.
  - Burns, Marilyn J. Pocahontas Blood, Being an Index to "Pocahontas, Alias Matoaka, and Her Descendants through Her Marriage at Jamestown, Virginia, in April, 1614, with John Rolfe, Gentleman." Silver Spring, Md.: The Virginia Tree 1983., 126; 16 leaves.
    See: Wyndham Robertson, Pocahontas, Alias Matoaka... (ENTRY 360).
  - Campbell, Charles. History of the Colony and Ancient Dominion of Virginia. Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott and Co. 1860., 127; 765 pp.
    Ends with the victory at Yorktown, 1781
    Enlarged from the author's Introduction to the History of the Colony and Ancient Dominion of Virginia (1847)Includes index.
  - Campbell, John Wilson. A History of Virginia from Its Discovery till the Year 1781, with Biographical Sketches of All the Most Distinguished Characters That Occur in the Colonial, Revolutionary, or Subsequent Period of Our History. Petersburg Va.: 1813., 128; 310 pp.
    Campbell, an Ohio lawyer and politician, was a native of Augusta County, Va., and an amateur historianIncludes a "Sketch of the History of the Church in Virginia" (pp. 287-310).
  - Caroline County (Va.) Jamestown Festival Observance Committee. Caroline County Historical Guide Book., 129; 80 pp.; illus.
  - Carrier, Lyman. Agriculture in Virginia, 1607-1699. 1957., 130; 41 pp.; illus.
    Bibliography: 35-36
    Reprint: Charlottesville, University Press of Virginia, 1970.
  - Carson, Jane. Bacon's Rebellion, 1676-1976. 1976., 131; V, 91 pp.; map.
  - Caywood, Louis R. Excavations at Green Spring Plantation. 1955., 132; V, 29 pp.; illus. (part folded).
    An archaeological report prepared for the Virginia 350th Anniversary Commission and the Jamestown-Williamsburg-Yorktown Celebration Commission.
  - Cecil-Williams, John. Goodwill Missions to the United States of America. 1960., 133; [17] pp.
    Includes some discussion of a visit to the Jamestown FestivalDetached from The Transactions of the Honourable Society of Cummrodorian (1960): 112-28.
  - Chamber of Commerce (Roanoke, Va.) Roanoke, Virginia: Its Location, Climate and Water Supply; Its Manufacturing, Commercial and Educational Advantages and General Desirability as a Place of Residence., 134; 32 pp.; illus., portraits.
    Compiled and edited under the auspices of the Jamestown Exposition Committee byE. B. Jacobs, secretary, Chamber of Commerce.
  - Chamber of Commerce (Williamsburg, Va.) The Cradle of the Republic: Williamsburg, Jamestown, Yorktown; The Historic Virginia Peninsula between the York and James Rivers. [1925?], 135; 15 pp.; illus.
  - Chesapeake Steamship Company. A Short Journey to the Cradle of the Nation: Historic Yorktown, Williamsburg, and Jamestown. [1923?], 136; [16] pp.; illus.
  - Clement, Maud Carter. The Early Homes of Chatham, an Old Virginia Courthouse Town, in Recognition of the Jamestown Festival, 1957. [1957]., 137; 47 pp.; illus.
  - College of William and Mary. The College of William and Mary in Virginia and the Jamestown Festival of 1957. 1958., 138; 29 pp.; illus., portraits.
    Prepared by James A. Servies in collaboration with J. T. Baldwin, Jr.
  - Colonial Dames of America, Virginia. Presentation by the Colonial Dames of America in the State of Virginia of the Robert Hunt Memorial Shrine to the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities: Programme of Its Dedication at Jamestown Island, Va., June 15, 1922 (Magna Charta Day). 1922., 139; [19] pp.
  - Cooke, John Esten. Virginia: A History of the People. 1884., 140; Xxi, 523 pp.; map.
    Covers mainly the colonial period of Virginia history.
  - Copland, Patrick, and Peter Pope. Virginia's God Be Thanked; or, A Sermon of Thanksgiving for the Happie Successe of the Affayres in Virginia This Last Yeare, Preached by Patrick Copland at Bow-Church in Cheapside, before the Honorable Virginia Company, on Thursday, the 18 of Aprill 1622; Hereunto Are Adjoyned Some Epistles, Written First in the Latine (and Now Englished) in the East Indies by Peter Pope, an Indian Youth Who Was Baptised in London, December 22, 1616. 1622., 141; 36 pp.
    Contains information concerning the products of Virginia, the condition of the colony, and its relations with the Indians.
  - Costa, Tom. An Illustrated History of the Jamestown Exposition., 1198; 45 pp.; illus., maps.
  - Cotter, John L. Archeological Excavations at Jamestown Colonial National Historical Park and Jamestown National Historic Site, Virginia. 1958., 142; X, 299 pp.; illus., maps (1 folded).
    The report includes all recorded exploration at Jamestown up to 1958. It documents the archeological work at Jamestown, provides basic field data on the architecture, artifacts and community structure, and summarizes these data so as to indicate the way of life which was developing in Virginia during the seventeenth century. Excavations revealed aboriginal remains, a Confederate fort, several churches, two cemeteries and a large number of dwellings and outbuildings. A summary discusses life at Jamestown and how it changed under the conditions of the New World. There are appendices on ceramics, other artifacts, and floral and faunal remains. [Author]Bibliography: 195-99. Includes index
    Folded map in pocket: Archeological Base Map of the Site of "James Towne.".. (ENTRY 1039)Second edition: Courtland, Archeological Society of Virginia, 1994
    This report became the author's Ph.D. dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, 1959 (ENTRY 66).
  - Cotter, John L., and J. Paul Hudson. New Discoveries at Jamestown, Site of the First Successful English Settlement in America. 1957., 143; 99 pp.; illus.
    An illustrated report of archaeological finds at Jamestown, concentrating on artifacts, and devoting little space to featuresBibliography: 98-99
    Reprint: 1962.
  - Couture, Richard T. To Preserve and Protect: A History of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities. 1984., 1199; 207 pp.; illus.
    Bibliography: 182-83. Includes index.
  - Craven, Wesley Frank. The Dissolution of the Virginia Company: The Failure of a Colonial Experiment. 1932., 144; 350 pp.
    Reprint: Gloucester, Mass., Peter Smith, 1964.
  - ---. The Southern Colonies in the Seventeenth Century, 1607-1689. A History of the South, vol. 1. 1949., 145; Xv, 451 pp.; illus.
    Includes bibliographical references, a critical essay on authorities (417-33), and an index.
  - ---. The Virginia Company of London, 1606-1624. 1957., 146; 57 pp.; illus.
    Reprints: Charlottesville, University Press of Virginia, 1970; Baltimore, Genealogical Publishing Co., 1993.
  - Dabney, Virginius. Jamestown before the Mayflower., 147; 15 pp.; illus., portraits.
    This article originally appeared September 29, 1957, in The New York Times Magazine.
  - ---. A Triple Shrine of History Linking Jamestown, Where America's Colonial Period Began, Yorktown, Where It Ended, and Old Williamsburg; A "Colonial National Monument" Is Being Created by the Federal Government in Virginia, Where This Historical Tract Is To Be Set Aside as a National Shrine 1930., 148; 8 pp.
    Reprinted by permission from New York Herald Tribune, Sunday, October 5, 1930.
  - Darling, Flora Adams. 1607-1907, Memories of Virginia: A Souvenir of Founding Days. 1907., 149
    Includes a historical sketch of Samuel Mathews, an extended memorial poem, and an account of events at the Jamestown Exposition.
  - Davis, J. E. (Jane Eliza). Jamestown and Her Neighbors on Virginia's Historic Peninsula. [1928]., 150; Ix, 100 pp.; front., illus.
    Some of the chapters in the present volume were included in a book called Round about Jamestown... [ENTRY 151] They have been thoroughly revised and brought up to date and much new material has been added. [Foreword]
  - ---. Round about Jamestown: Historical Sketches of the Lower Virginia Peninsula., 151; 104, [3] pp.; front. (folded map), plates.
    Most of the half tones used in illustration are loaned by the Southern workman, of Hampton, Virginia, in which magazine these sketches first appeared. [Preface]Includes index
    See the author's Jamestown and Her Neighbors on Virginia's Historic Peninsula (ENTRY 150).
  - Davis, John. Life and Surprising Adventures of the Celebrated John Smith, First Settler of Virginia, Interspersed with Interesting Anecdotes of Pocahontas, an Indian Princess. 1813., 152; 72 pp.
    Includes "Life of John Robinson": [59]-72.
  - Davis, Richard Beale. George Sandys, Poet-Adventurer: A Study in Anglo-American Culture in the Seventeenth Century. 1955., 153